Both the engineers are working on
the same task.
What is that task?
Classify whether given this email is
a spam or not.
But for the code you wrote and the
code written by the senior
developer,
the cost difference is 450 times.
Yes, there is a cost difference of
450 times.
On the left side, this is the code
you wrote.
A junior developer.
When you wrote, someone said,
Bro, always use the best model.
So what did you do?
You pick the ChatGPT 5.5,
which is the latest model,
and you put the highest effort
reasoning.
And the code was executed.
And it works perfectly fine.
And what was the answer?
No, that's good.
But the cost it took to answer that
is 0.0028 dollars.
This looks like a very small amount,
doesn't it?
Just remember that.
And now see, on the right side,
this is me, a senior engineer.
Same company, same task,
same question.
But here I picked a smaller model
and almost turned off the thinking.
And what was the answer again?
The same answer, no.
But how much is the cost?
0.000006 dollars.
Same answer, same one word.
But what is the difference between
these two?
470 times the cost.
Now you can look at these two
numbers and think,
Bro, the cost is very,
very, very small, isn't it?
But that is where you will fall into
the trap.
Imagine, you are sending 1 lakh API
requests every day in the company.
And if you estimate the cost,
Every day, they will get a bill of
23,000 rupees for the code written
by the junior engineer.
That is, they will get a bill of
only 50 rupees for the code written
by the senior engineer.
Same code, same output,
but different model choice,
different architectural decisions.
Outside, many YouTubers will say,
Use ChatGPT 5.5, use Claude Opus
4.8, use 4.7 maximum thinking.
Nobody shows you this number.
Because they don't even know.
Because even ChatGPT doesn't show
you these numbers.
And I know because I am someone
building agents in production at a
large scale in the industry right
now.
And this is the gap that I see.
And that is the knowledge that I
want to fill and give it to you
guys.
And companies are looking for such
skills.
If you want to become an agent AI
developer in 2026,
In the next 15 minutes,
I am going to teach you exactly the
same.
But we will start with the cost.
We will first understand where the
problem is coming from.
Let me also explain.
This is a video in our roadmap.
If you haven't watched our last
video,
Our phase 2 starting video,
What actually an LLM is.
What is LLM?
How does it train?
What are the components?
And if you haven't watched that
video,
Please pause it.
Go back and watch that video and
come back here and continue.
You will get even better
understanding.
And now we will cover a mix of 2.2
and 2.3 in this video.
In reality, there are only 3
controls when LLM calls.
Creativity, effort and layout.
What does creativity do?
It will decide how safe or wild the
next prediction token is.
What did we think in the last video?
They are just predicting the next
probabilistic word.
That's it.
So that next word will control how
much creativity should be there.
And second is effort.
You must have heard about effort.
We have a lot of reasoning models.
They will think before they answer.
They are little bit more powerful.
Because they have thinking
capability.
And the third part is layout.
What is this layout?
It will come down to your mistakes.
How do you write prompts?
Many times, many people think that
the more the prompt, the better.
But there is a complete art inside
prompt engineering.
Depending on your prompt,
Your output tokens, input tokens and
cost are changing a lot.
Once you understand these 3
parameters,
You will never write the code like a
junior developer.
The first thing we will understand
is about creativity.
To control creativity,
There is a parameter called
temperature in OpenAI API.
Temperature values go from 0 to 2.
When temperature value changes,
Creativity changes in our output.
Creativity changes.
Here we have a code.
What is that code?
I am connecting to an OpenAI API.
What is the question here?
5 startup ideas for AI in India.
It is my prompt.
What am I doing?
I am creating 2 temperature values.
0 and 0.9
After that,
I am using OpenAI API chat
completion.
I am using a model which is called
GPT 4.1 mini.
I am not using GPT 5 or 5.5.
I will explain why in a minute.
Here are our messages.
What is the role?
Our user.
What is the content?
This is what our prompt is.
Then we are setting up the
temperature as well.
Then we are also printing the
outputs.
Let us look at the output by
executing this piece of code.
It is taking a lot of time.
When temperature is 0,
AI powered Agritech platform,
AI based regional language learning
app,
AI driven healthcare diagnostic for
rural areas
and smart AI chartboards for
government services
and AI based skill development for
job matching platform.
This is good.
But when our temperature is 0.9,
we are on the higher side of
creativity.
Then if you look at this,
AI powered Agritech platform,
AI based regional language tutoring
app,
AI enhanced healthcare diagnostic
for rural areas
and smart AI credit scoring for
informal sector
and AI powered personal e -commerce
recommendations
for tier 2 and tier 3 cities.
This is good.
So there are some common values in
both.
But there is a difference in the
ideas.
Isn't it?
Now what we are going to do is,
let us try to execute the same piece
of code again
and see if there is a change in the
difference
in the output as well or not.
So let us try.
And now look again.
AI powered Agritech platform
and AI based regional language
learning,
AI driven healthcare diagnostics,
smart AI chartboards
and AI based skill assessment.
If you noticed,
even when we executed last time,
I got the same 5 outputs
when the temperature is 0.
That means there is little
creativity.
It is just predicting as per its
learning pattern.
And for the next time,
when our temperature value is 0.9,
if you look at the output,
these names are the same.
But see the format and the content
it provided.
What is the problem and what is the
solution?
In the starting,
it just gave me the ideas.
But when the creativity is high,
every time when you execute the same
piece of code,
our output will change.
When our creativity is in the zone,
almost it is guaranteed that
every time you execute the same
code,
you are going to get the same
output.
Now we have a twist.
What is that twist?
I am using the same piece of code.
But I just changed the model to GPT
-5.
And then temperature is equal to,
let us say, 0.
And let us try to execute this piece
of code.
And see,
I got an API error
which is called Bad Request Error.
Error code is 400.
If you have not seen my API video,
go ahead and watch that video
and come back and continue.
Because if you watch that video,
you will understand exactly
what this error code is.
If you notice,
we are using the same code and same
kind of models.
Both are from the beginning.
But they are not working at the same
time.
Don't you think it is weird?
What they did in the beginning is,
they divided their models
into two different segments.
One group of models will accept
the input as temperature.
And there are other set of models
which they don't accept
the temperature as input.
Then how can you control
the output of these models?
Yeah, that is where
reasoning comes into picture.
But before that,
let's also understand
the values of temperature
and how the output
is going to change.
So, if you look at here,
the value of temperature
is between 0 to 0.3.
That means the temperature is very
low
and the model is highly focused
and deterministic.
It will almost select
the highest probability word.
And as the temperature increases,
the creativity also increases.
So, whenever
you want the LLM
to behave the same way
in every LLM call,
always try to put the temperature
as low as possible.
If you are working as a creative
director,
then try to bump up
the temperature to 1 or 2.
But most of the times,
if you put the temperature from 0.5
to 1.0,
your work is going to get satisfied.
Otherwise,
if you are using latest models,
you cannot use this temperature.
It is not only with open AI.
Even C4.8 or C4.7
will not take the temperature as an
input.
Then what should we do?
That is where we will learn about
the second step which is called the
effort.
Now let's understand
reasoning with an example.
Look here, the same piece of code
but I am using
model GPT 5.5.
This is my input question.
Plan a 3 -day trip to Hyderabad
for a family of 4.
We are using one extra line
which is called reasoning.
This effort should be
low, high or maximum.
If you observe,
the latest models
GPT 5.5,
OPUS 4.8, 4.7
all of these models
will not accept
the old parameter which is called
temperature.
How do you control the creativity?
That is why
they got this reasoning.
What does it mean?
Whenever you prompt a question,
these LLMs will plan ahead
how to answer this question
and they will start answering
for your question.
I told you that they will think
internally.
Even they will consume
the tokens as well.
Those are what we call
hidden tokens.
Let me quickly go to the
documentation page of OpenAI.
This is the documentation page
for reasoning models.
Always it is best to use
documentation by official companies.
Look here, reasoning models
like GPT 5.5
uses internal reasoning tokens.
This is very important.
This is not the last year.
This year we have all of these
things.
The content you learnt last year
has changed right now.
If you look at this one
I am using the same piece of code
these contain
either none,
low, medium, high
and extra high.
These are all the reasoning
capabilities that we can choose
and by default
GPT 5.5
means it defaults to
medium reasoning model.
Let's say, you asked me
it takes some time for me to
execute this code.
Let me show you the output.
I am using GPT 5.5
and I got this output
and at the end I also
printed how many tokens that we are
using
and what is the cost as well.
Look here, input token is 20
based on the question we got
output token is 20, total token is
and the total cost
as per GPT 5.5 model
we have 2.7 rupees.
To do all this print
I created a function
what we did here
cost per million tokens
for input, output and cached
tokens
so I got all of these numbers
from the OpenAI documentation
and current USD to INR
ratio is 97 rupees
and then I am printing all of these
details
what I am printing
I am getting the token usage
after getting the token usage
I am calculating the cost based upon
the token usage
and I am printing everything
in a proper formatted way
and we got this output.
But
one thing I wanted to say is
now let's try one more question
that question is
little bit complex
you are given this broken python
function
it is not correct
and what is the task for LLM?
find all the bugs in the functions
explain why each bug matters
and rewrite the function correctly
and add 5 test cases including every
education
this is a little costly prompt
so if I show you the code
again same print
nothing too complex, same print
almost
but
I am calling the same LLM
with different different effort
levels
so one is none, then low
then medium, then high
and extra high
so same question, you are choosing
the same model
with different reasoning
capabilities
now let's look at the output
so the output is almost same
because the question we were given
is not
a complex question
see if you are using no reasoning at
all
you are consuming 111 inputs
and then you are
having output of 1581
and there are no hidden
reasoning tokens
because we kept reasoning at none
and the total cost is
3.98 rupees to answer this question
that is perfectly good
but for the same question
if I choose a low reasoning model
then here
it has hidden tokens of 127
means internally
and the cost became
4.4, there is a small jump
and then if I go to medium
then the number of internal
reasoning tokens bump to a lot
to become 1000
and the cost becomes
5.8 and if I go to
high, our input will be same
but see here
reasoning model is less
I don't know why it happens
but here reasoning model is less
and the cost is 4.07
but look at extra high
here reasoning will take
7768 tokens
and for the same question
you are spending 22 rupees
and it's almost
15 or 20x difference
in the cost
so same model, same question
we did one parameter and the cost
has been
20 times
so what we are learning here is
you as an engineer
who is building all of these LLM
agentic applications
you need to decide
what kind of task, what kind of
model
to use
so what this is
we have a rocket
so you need to decide
what kind of model
to use
so that's how you need to decide
then you can optimize a lot
and that is the exact mistake
that junior developer has done
in the first step
he always use the top
model with top high reasoning
capability
but what he did
he decided to use
the smaller model or previous
generation model and then he got
the cost as very very very less
that is the difference that makes
or breaks an AI engineer
and the lesson here is
not always use cheap model
there might be some tasks
which 5.5 extra high
reasoning would be really good
let's say coding agents
they need to think, think and act
upon it
and they need to work in a
loop, in such case reasoning
models work really good
so according to our use case
you need to decide what kind of
model
to use
and it applies to all the other
models
as well, Claude or Gemini
but we will talk about the
comparison
of all of these models in the next
video
so stay tuned for that one
it's going to be very interesting
and this 3rd part layout
is not going to go anywhere
guys, in 2027 or 2028
maybe even in ChatGPT version 7
this is going to stay same
not like our temperature
so let me come back to this one
there is a paper which is called
lost in the middle
it's a very famous paper that
released in 2023
but we will not go through all the
technical details here
the only important thing is
if you look at this graph
there is this U graph
the meaning is
the bigger your prompt is
the starting elements,
ending elements
are very important for models
and the middle elements
are going to get not that much
important
that is what we are going to
understand here
now instead of this paper
let's understand this in a simpler
way
so we have a graph
this is the graph
let's say you have written a big
prompt
so at that time
the starting parts of the prompt
will get high attention
what is attention?
we talked in our last video
how LLMs are built
if you haven't watched that video
please go ahead and watch that video
and come back to this one again
and for the middle part
it is little bit under weighted
it will also have importance
but not as much as the importance
from the first and the last
so this is a very important aspect
burying the important stuff
inside middle of very long prompt
is bad for the model's output
okay
why and where do we use this?
the important thing is
whenever you write
a big instruction
for any model
always put the critical instructions
near the start
and repeat critical instructions
or rules at the end again
and even for large context windows
this rule is going to get
applicable
you might think
that I will fill the whole book
with 1 million context
even in that scenario
the starting and the ending
tokens are getting more important
compared to the middle tokens
you might think
let's say you have written
10 pages letter
do you think that person reads every
single thing?
maybe he will read first thing and
last thing
that's how the models are also doing
that's how the model's output
will also affect
and this U curve is exactly
why the naive rag
the retrieval argumented generation
will fail
we will not talk about this right
now
we have a specific dedicated video
on the rag as well
but
we will learn
in another topic
which is called the art of
prompt engineering
so let's summarize everything that
we have learned
in this video
we have 3 methods
the first one is the creativity
we will change something called as
temperature
otherwise
this temperature is only applicable
for the older models
not applicable for the later models
and the second one
which is called the effort
what is this effort?
which is the reasoning
when you prompt something
an answer should come
how much you should think internally
they have multiple modes
small, medium, high
extra high
so you can decide
on which question you want the
reasoning
and the third one
which is called the layout
when you design a prompt
the important stuff
if you put it in the beginning or
the end
they will have more attention
compared to the middle stuff
so after learning all this
what are you going to do?
you can decide
how much model you should use
and you can print all of these
outputs
and see the difference visually
this is what makes a difference
between a well versed engineer
and the new one who is starting out
and
we are going to talk
in the next video
which is
when we have base models,
reasoning models
high efficient models
which model to use when
and how are they going to perform
and we are going to understand
the model benchmarks and evaluation
based on that
you will understand exactly
which model to use
with this video
if you have learned something new
please consider subscribing
and let's target the likes of
500 or 1000
and if you know someone who needs
this video
please share it with them